<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The religious rebel a sermon preach'd at South-Marston near Hyworth in Wiltshire, on the ninth of September, being the day of publick thanksgiving for the deliverance of His Majesty's sacred person, his royal brother, and the government from the late hellish fanatick conspiracy / by Charles Powell.</title>
            <author>Powell, Charles, b. 1644 or 5-1685 or 6.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55538</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3046</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3301</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11951515</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11951515</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51446</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55538)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51446)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 820:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The religious rebel a sermon preach'd at South-Marston near Hyworth in Wiltshire, on the ninth of September, being the day of publick thanksgiving for the deliverance of His Majesty's sacred person, his royal brother, and the government from the late hellish fanatick conspiracy / by Charles Powell.</title>
                  <author>Powell, Charles, b. 1644 or 5-1685 or 6.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms X, 10 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51446:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Religious Rebel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON PREACH'D AT SOUTH-MARSTON NEAR HYWORTH IN WILTSHIRE, On the Ninth of <hi>September;</hi> BEING The Day of Publick Thankſgiving for the Deliverance of His Majeſty's Sacred Perſon, His Royal Brother, and the Government, from the late Helliſh Fanatick Conſpiracy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> CHARLES POWELL, <hi>M.A. Sometime</hi> Student <hi>of</hi> Chriſt-Church <hi>in</hi> Oxford.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby</hi> at the <hi>Biſhops-Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:51446:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51446:2"/>
            <head>TO THE GENEROUS AND PIOUS, ASSERTOR OF LOYALTY And the True PROTESTANT RELIGION, THE HONOURABLE Sir <hi>THOMAS CVTLER,</hi> One of his <hi>Majeſty</hi>'s Deputy Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants, Juſtice of the Peace and <hi>Quorum</hi> for the <hi>County</hi> of <hi>Glouce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> and Captain in his <hi>Majeſty</hi>'s Royal Cittadel at <hi>PLYMOVTH,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHat You have ſo often fought for, and the Church of England has ſo long pray'd for, it has pleaſed the great
<pb facs="tcp:51446:3"/>King of Kings in Mercy at laſt to bring to paſs, the diſcovery, and thereby, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment of the Enemies of this Church and State. For which as we are all bound to render our unfeigned Thanks to the Almighty, (who alone gives Victory to Kings, and has once more preſerved our Royal <hi>David</hi> from the hands of <hi>Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirſty and deceitful Men.)</hi> So have none more reaſon to rejoyce before the <hi>Lord,</hi> than thoſe that ſerve at his <hi>Altar,</hi> and were deſigned to be Sacrificed upon it. And among thoſe, none more than your poor Servant, whoſe unfeigned (though uſeleſs) Loyalty has been ſo long coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Crime, that it can ſcarce yet render him acceptable to thoſe men, who ſay to the Miniſters of the Goſpel,
<pb facs="tcp:51446:3"/>as the Rebellious Jews did to the <hi>Prophets</hi> of old; <hi>Speak unto us ſmooth things, Prophecy deceits; Get you out of the way; turn aſide out of the path: cauſe the Holy One of Iſrael to ceaſe from us.</hi> But bleſſed be God, who has preſerved the <hi>Clergy</hi> of the Church of England from the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition of Popery, and the Atheiſtcal Hipocriſy of Fanaticiſm. To both which, as the whole World can witneſs your Loyal and Zealous Averſion; ſo am I bound in Gratitude to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the great Encouragements I have always received from your Generous Bounty in that narrow Sphere, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I move; For which I can onely offer up my Prayers to the Great God of
<pb facs="tcp:51446:4"/>Recompences; That be would still con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue you in that true Religion, which you have received from ſo many Noble, ſo many Honourable Anceſtors, in the deſerved Favour of the beſt of Princes, and the beſt Judge of Worthy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and in the due Reſpect and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of all Loyal Men, among whom be pleas'd to admit of the moſt humble, moſt gratefull Acknowledgments of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>Your much Obliged and very Faithful Servant, <hi>C. P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51446:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PSAL. X. 10.</bibl>
                  <p>He falleth down and humbleth himſelf, that the Congregation of the Poor may fall into the hands of his Captains.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>REbellion (ſays <hi>Samuel</hi>) <hi>is as the Sin of Witchcraſt;</hi> Nor need we ſeek far for proof of his Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſince they both betray themſelves to be the Offspring of the ſame Father. Satan firſt rebelled againſt the great Monarch of the whole World, and, though his Ambition tumbled him down from the bright Regions of Bliſs into eternal Chains of Darkeneſs, yet his Inſtruments carry on the ſame Rebellion ſtill; though the Scene be changed, and the Plot carried on at a diſtance, the Deſign is ſtill the ſame, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that our earthly Rebels are in this the worſe Devils, that they dare rebel againſt God and the King too. Nor do they in any thing more reſemble the firſt Founder of their Society, and the perpetual Preſident of their Dark Cabal, than that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51446:5"/>all their unſucceſsfulneſs doth rather en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hance than abate their Malice, onely drive them the more deſperately on, though they are convinced that Heaven it ſelf, and all that is called God be arm'd againſt them, and all the Powers of Hell and Darkeneſs not able to protect them from that Fate, which they ſeem to hug, becauſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not avoid. To ſearch the Records of all back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Ages of the World, and ſhew you this black Spirit working in the Sons of Perdition ever ſince there was a Monarchy on Earth, which, I am ſure, is the Ancienteſt and, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, the beſt Government in the World, inſtituted by God himſelf, the great King of Kings, by whom all Kings reign, and from whom alone they derive their Power, as being the onely Repreſentatives of the Celeſtiall Polity; (for in Heaven there's no Republick.) This would be as far from the buſineſs of the Text, as it is, from my Intentions; let it ſuffice that I have choſen an inſtance in the Reign of him, who was not only Anointed by Gods immediate command, but in a more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall manner a Type of Gods Anointed, Chriſt the Lord; perſecuted and haraſſed by that very Brood, whoſe unhappy Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51446:5"/>crucifi'd the King of Glory. Holy <hi>David</hi> (we all know) had troubles more than enough, and the more, becauſe he was Holy <hi>(all that will live godly in Chriſt Ieſus ſhall ſuffer Perſecution)</hi> whoſe whole life, though it were but one continued Scene of Afflictions, yet we find his Croſs doubled, when he came to the Crown: The out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſplendor of which, though it be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired by all, yet is it's intrinſick Weight and Burthen underſtood by few, but thoſe that bear it. But of all the Troubles, which like Thornes ſtuffd his Diadem, and peirc'd his Sacred Temples, we find none ſtrike ſo deep, as that which occaſion'd this Pſalm and Text, <hi>Viz.</hi> a Rebellious Son, and a Perfidious Favorite; The one of whom, as he might reaſonably have expected to be the Staff of his Age; ſo might he juſtly have hoped, that the other by his Wiſdom and Counſel ſhould have guarded his Crown and Dignity, who was exalted to ſo great Eminency in the State, and admitted to ſuch an Intimacy with his Prince. But alas! we ſee, (and I wiſh we had never ſeen it) that the beſt of Princes cannot tranſmit Vertue with their Blood; nor infuſe Gratitude, where they beſtow their greateſt Favors.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51446:6"/>Let <hi>Abſolom</hi> be never ſo dearly beloved and careſs'd by a tender <hi>David?</hi> yet a little Popular Air ſhall ſtifle his Duty to him, who gave him Life; Let <hi>Achitophel</hi> be raiſed never ſo high by the Beams of Majeſty; yet the next blazing Comet ſhall make him forget the benign Influences of that Sun, that exalted him from the Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill to ſet him among the Princes of the People. I hope you do not ſuſpect, that I am going about to draw that Parallel, which is ſo obvious to every eye, and has already been the task of ſo many Satyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Pens; I remember I am this day to Preach; and 'tis below the Sacred buſineſs of the Pulpit to ſtab with Gooſe Quills, or execute Malefactors with Invectives. <hi>David</hi> tell us,<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.5.</note> that <hi>Gods Arrows are ſharp in the hearts of the Kings Enemies;</hi> and we need not add ſharpneſs there, where Conſcience daily ſets the Edge;<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 2, 1.</note> yet ſince <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, that <hi>To every thing there is a Seaſon,</hi> and he that would be accounted a Faithful Steward in Chriſts Family,<note place="margin">Math. 24.45.</note> muſt give the Houſhold, as <hi>their Meat, ſo in due Seaſon</hi> too. I hope the preſent face of things will juſtify my choice of the Subject now before us, and if you cannot chooſe but make the Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51446:6"/>your ſelves, upon their Heads be it, who gave the Cue. That I may not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore diſappoint you of a Sermon by a tedious Preface, or by making A pologies for my Diſcourſe before hand, (which yet not long ſince they had need to do, that durſt ſpeak Loyalty even in the Pulpit) give me leave to lead you to the Text, by looking a little back on the Context, which will give you the occaſion of the <hi>Pſalm,</hi> and the meaning of the words I am to inſiſt on.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Pſalm</hi> therefore in general is a Pathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical complaint of <hi>David</hi> to Almighty God, of the Pride, Treachery, Malice and Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of wicked Men, who (as his Son, the wiſeſt of Kings, ſays) <hi>ſeek only Rebellion;</hi> and theſe wicked men (Expoſitors tell us,) are thoſe whom he had maintain'd and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd in his own Court, and therefore were the more wicked, and the more dangerous; Of which very Perſons he ſays: <hi>It is not an Open Enemy that hath done me this diſhonour, for then I could have born it: Neither was it mine Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, that did magnify himſelf againſt me: for then (peradventure) I would have hid my ſelf from him. But it was thou, even my Companion, my Guide, and mine own Familiar Friend; We took ſweet Counſell together, and walked
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51446:7"/>in the Houſe of God as Friends.</hi> And this very well agrees with the Character in my Text. For though in the former part of the <hi>Pſalm,</hi> we have the Lion drawn Rampant, roaring out his Cruel and Bloody Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſcorning all Reſiſtance, either from God or Man, as if he were ſure of his prey, boaſting of his hearts deſire, and confident that he could not be moved, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6. Yet, leſt this boyſterous noiſe might rouze the Royall Game, and make them provide for their own ſecurity; in my Text and the two preceding <hi>Verſes,</hi> we find him in another poſture; though he will in no wiſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake his Lioniſh Ferity and Cruelty, yet he will draw on the Fox's Skin to conceal it, and therefore he turns Huntſman, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 8. He ſits lurking in the ſecret places of the Villages, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he lurk's among the Rich Farmers and Country men; among thoſe who are moſt likely to be drawn in by his glozing and ſpecious Pretences, and there he lyes ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as a Lion in his Den, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 9. and there <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, fut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon his Neſt, wrap'd in an Hypocritital garb of Humility and Piety, he falls down, and humbles himſelf, <hi>that the Congregation
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51446:7"/>of the Poor may fall into the hands of his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that my Text is the Character of a Religious Rebel, a Villain; for ſo it will eaſily appear, if we look on the words, either as a part of the foregoing Metaphor, or as a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of him, who was the occaſion of this querulous <hi>Pſalm, viz.</hi> the Rebellious <hi>Ah<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolom,</hi> who humbly beg's leave to go to <hi>Hebron;</hi> not to pay his Vow to the Lord,<note place="margin">2 Sam: 15, 7</note> as he falſly pretended, but to prepare a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt his King; not out of any regard to Religion, but to ſerve his own Ambition; not to ſerve God, but his own Intereſt; where <hi>he falls down</hi> indeed, and ſeem's <hi>to humble himſelf</hi> to God, but in the ſame poſture Courts the People; and all this, <hi>that the Congregation of the Poor,</hi> the <hi>Caetus Inopum,</hi> the Multitude of Poor helpleſs People, that knew not his Drifts, nor were prepared to reſiſt him, <hi>might fall into the hands</hi> and power of his voracious Followers, or as it is according to the 70. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that himſelf may Lord it over the Poor.</p>
            <p>Diviſions are of late ſo dangerous, that I ſhall not dare ſo much as to divide my Text, and therefore ſhall only raiſe from it one Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51446:8"/>which I hope to prove more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, than ever proceeded either from the <hi>Roman</hi> Chair, or the <hi>Geneva</hi> Claſſis: And that is this, That it is no new thing for the Worſt of men to make uſe of the Sacred Name of Religion, to palliate the moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable Undertakings. Blood-ſhed, the Murther of the Fathers and Defenders of Religion, pious Kings and Princes, deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Maſſacre of their fellow Subjects, pulling down and overturning of all Order and Polity in the world, muſt be all uſherd in (as we ſee it this day) with the Lamb-like, harmleſs voyce of Religion: And though in theſe Glorious times of the Goſpel they cannot poſſibly think ſo, yet they will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, that in all this they do God ſervice; ſo true is that of our Saviour;<note place="margin">Math. 7.15.</note> 
               <hi>They come to us in Sheeps cloathing, but inwardly they are ravening Wolves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Propoſition has been ſo often, and ſo ſadly proved, even among our ſelves, that to go about to confirm it by Arguments or Preſidents, were to light you with a Lanthorn in the Sunſhine, or to perſwade you that you are wounded, when you are roaring under the ſmart and anguiſh of the blow. Yet, ſince the Sincerity of our Religion, and the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51446:8"/>Juſtice of our Nation will not ſuffer us to paſs Sentence upon any thing without full proof, let me beg your patience, while I call an Evidence or two out of the Record of Scripture, and the Chronicles of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ages; which, though they do not ſpeak <hi>(vivà voce,)</hi> as Witneſſes in Temporal Courts uſe and ought to do, yet ſince their Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is handed down to us by the <hi>Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Spirit of God,</hi> who neither will deceive, nor can be deceived; I hope we need not fear an <hi>Ingnoramus</hi> on the Bill; for if Men <hi>believe not Moſes and the Prophets, neither will they believe, though one aroſe from the Dead,</hi> to teſtify his Knowledge of the thing.</p>
            <p>That I may not therefore inſtance in matters of Private Concerns (in which alſo wicked Men palliate their Evil Deſigns with the ſhew of Piety and Religion) I ſhall confine my-ſelf to that which is more properly the Buſineſs of the Day, <hi>viz.</hi> Rebellion againſt Lawful Kings and Princes; Of which the Firſt that offers it ſelf to us in Holy Writ, is that remarkable one of <hi>Corah</hi> and his Company againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> the meekeſt Man upon all the Earth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the moſt likely to have retain'd the Love and Allegiance of his People, had he not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51446:9"/>been to deal with <hi>a Stiff-necked and Rebellious Generation,</hi> of whom God himſelf ſays by his <hi>Prophet,</hi> that they were <hi>Rebellious from their Youth up;</hi> even in the Infancy of their Government they began to be Rebellious. And this Rebellion we find uſher'd in with the pretext of Religon. For though <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> govern'd them by Laws both Temporal and Spiritual, which were dictated by God himſelf; yet in the Pride of their Hearts they thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves already ſo perfect in what they could teach them, that they were become a Law to themſelves, and therefore counted it a piece of Uſurpation, an Invaſion of their Privileges, for the Prince to command, or the Prieſt to preſume to teach thoſe, who now thought themſelves fit to be Teachers of others, and therefore ſay they, <hi>Ye take too much upon you, you Moſes and Aaron; are not all the Congregation Holy as well as ye?</hi> and muſt we ſtill ſubmit to your Magiſterial Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands? No, we have Princes of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, that will vindicate our Liberties, and force a Toleration for us, that every Man may do, <hi>what ſeems good in his own eyes;</hi> we all know, as well as you, how to Serve and Worſhip God, and therefore will not any
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51446:9"/>longer be reſtrain'd by Human Authority. You have no Power over our Conſciences; that is Gods Prerogative; we have our Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from him; and rather than part with that, we will <hi>burſt your bonds aſunder, and caſt away your Cords from us.</hi> And had not Gods Providence and Care of future Ages Signalized this Primitive Rebellion with a Notorious and Miraculous Puniſhment, I am afraid, our Age would have argued it as a Preſident, and from thence have pleaded the Lawfulneſs of Rebelling for Liberty of Conſcience. For ever therefore bleſſed be the great King of Kings, who has ſet forth their Puniſhment as a Landmark for others to avoid the ſame Rock; And thrice bleſſed be his Glorious Name, who has ſo Graciouſly deliver'd our meek <hi>Moſes</hi> and our Pious <hi>Aarons</hi> from the Bloody Zeal of thoſe Sons of Rebellion, who with the falſe Name of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion would this Day have extirpated the beſt Government and the Pureſt Religion in the World; Even ſo let all thine Enemies periſh, O Lord, but let thoſe that love him be as the Sun when he goeth forth in his Might!</p>
            <p>The next Inſtance we have of this, is that of <hi>Abſolom,</hi> who is now grown ſo ſtale a <hi>Theme,</hi> that you cannot but think it Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51446:10"/>though not impertinent, to mention him. We all know his pretended Zeal to Religion and Juſtice, the one of which was not pure enough for his Tender Conſcience at Court, but he muſt to <hi>Hebron to perform his Vow</hi> there; and the Other (as he falſely and Traiterouſly pretended) either perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or ſo ſlackly adminiſtred, that he gets him to the Gate, where in an Humble poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he proffers himſelf to the Rabble (who had need, I confeſs, of Severity of Juſtice to curb their Inſolencies) and there <hi>he falls down and Humbles himſelf before them; When any Man came nigh unto him, to do him Obeyſance, he put forth his hand and took him, and kiſſed him;</hi> and in the next <hi>Verſe</hi> 'tis ſaid, <hi>So Abſolom ſtole the hearts of the Men of Iſrael:</hi> But it is not long before we hear the paying of his Vow in <hi>Hebron,</hi> and his performance of Juſtice in the Gate; <hi>the Congregation of the Poor are fallen into the hands of his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains,</hi> and his King and Father forced to ſave his life by an Ignominious Flight. But once more and for ever praiſed be the great <hi>Jehovah,</hi> who deliver'd <hi>David</hi> his Servant from a Rebellious Son, and Ungrateful, and Perfidious Counſellor, who hung up that Trophy of his Juſtice, that Poſterity and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51446:10"/>future Ages might, <hi>ſee, and do no more ſo wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly!</hi> And let us pray, that all the Enemies of our Royal <hi>David, and all that riſe up againſt him to do him hurt, may be as that Young Man is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It would be too tedious now to diſplay <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam's</hi> Religious Stratagem to move the People to a Rebellion, by pretending to eaſe them of the Burthen of that Worſhip which was eſtabliſhed by Law at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and therefore inviting them to his own way of Worſhip, in places as remote, as he could, from the <hi>Royal City</hi> and <hi>Mother-Church,</hi> that ſo they might not be won by the Loyalty and Uniformity, which they ſhould ſee there, either to their Allegiance to the Houſe of <hi>David,</hi> or to <hi>David's</hi> Religion. I ſhall not trouble you with a Tranſcript of <hi>Joſephus,</hi> or <hi>Euſebius,</hi> concerning <hi>Theudas</hi> the Sorcerer (of whom St. <hi>Luke</hi> writes in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi>) who, that he might ſtir up the <hi>Jews</hi> to a Rebellion, called himſelf a Prophet, and told them, that for their Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance out of the hands of the Enemies of their Religion, he would work Wonders for them, make <hi>Jordan</hi> divide it ſelf as for their Forefathers of old, that they might eſcape out of the Idolatries of Egypt. Nor
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51446:11"/>ſhall I mention <hi>Judas</hi> the <hi>Galilean,</hi> who, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> tells us out of <hi>Joſephus,</hi> ſeduced the People of that Region to Rebellion, telling them that they ought not to ſuffer Humane Authority to rule over their Conſciences, or to preſcribe Laws in matter of Religion. Still it is <hi>in Nomine Domini,</hi> the Sacred Name of God is brought in to palliate their Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion; and how many cold Blaſts of this Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trin we have had from the Scotch-Horn, who under the Pretexts of Religion and Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation have permitted ſo few of our Sacred Kings Anceſtors to go in Peace to their Graves is fitter for Authority to remember, than for me to mention. Nor need I do it, ſince at this very day we ſee, that a Conſpiracy againſt the Life and covernment of the beſt of Kings, cannot be carry'd on without a Religious (I mean a <hi>Scotiſh</hi>) Agitator. I ſhall not trouble you therefore with more Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes (though they be almoſt innumerable) to prove the Truth of my Aſſertion, but ſhall conclude my Evidence with a Maxim of the wiſeſt of Kings, Prov. 17.11. <hi>An evil Man ſeeks only Rebellion, therefore a Cruel Meſſenger ſhall be ſent againſt him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now becauſe the End of all Sermons is Inſtruction, and the beſt Inſtruction is that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51446:11"/>which tends moſt to Practiſe; give me leave to draw down thoſe Practical Inferences, which are moſt Natural from the Text, and moſt Uſeful for our ſelves upon this Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>The firſt Inference therefore will be; That we have a care how we hearken to thoſe men, that make the greateſt Noiſe about Religion, which is not a thing of Talk and Noiſe and Tumult, but a Quiet, Calm, Peaceable thing. The Author of it was the Lamb of God, who neither ſtirred up the Jews to Rebell againſt the <hi>Roman</hi> Heathen <hi>Caeſar,</hi> nor did he ever make uſe of any Siniſter, or Violent Means to eſcape the hands of his Bloody Perſecutors and Crucifiers, who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied him for nothing more than his Religion which he came on Purpoſe to plant among them, and which was to be waterd with his own Blood, and brought to perfection by his own Death. But <hi>he was oppreſſed, and he was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iicted,</hi> yet <hi>he opened not his mouth; he was brought as a Lamb to the Slaughter, &amp; as a Sheep before her Shearers is dumb, ſo opened he not his mouth.</hi> Iſa. 53.7. As for Corruption in Religion, it was never ſo general among the Jews, as at his coming into the World; Yet in all his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons and Diſcourſes to them, (though ſome
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51446:12"/>times he was forc'd to pronounce a Woe to the Hypocritical Profeſſors, and Lewd livers among them) yet he never did (as he might have done) in the leaſt excite the <hi>Romans</hi> their Governors to perfecute or deſtroy them, but himſelf ſubmitted to them, that they might not take any Occaſion from his Practiſe to deal hardly with his Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men <hi>and Brethren according to the Fleſh,</hi> and exhorted all his Hearers to do ſo likewiſe, that they might not Pull down Vengeance on themſelves. In all his Actions in the whole Courſe of his Life, he was a Pattern to them of Meekneſs, Gentleneſs, Peaceable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Subjection. And truly, I am afraid, thoſe men, who make ſuch an Hurry and Clutter about Religion, are not his Diſciples, nor did they ever learn it from the King of Righteouſneſs and the Prince of Peace, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially when they make Religion the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Publick Commotions and Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances. And therefore it will neerly concern us to take St. <hi>John</hi>'s Advice, 1 Ep. 4 ch. 1. v. <hi>not to believe every Spirit, but to try the Spirits, whether they be of God;</hi> not to follow every Teacher, that pretends to be inſpir'd, but to make Tryal of all, that ſhall ſo pretend, by the Rules afforded them both by <hi>Moſes</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:51446:12"/>and <hi>Chriſt.</hi> For certainly there is no thing doth more truſh and hinder us in our Journey to the <hi>heavenly Canaan,</hi> than to ſtand ſtill, and liſten to every Whiſper, to every one that ſhall pull us by the Sleeve, and talk to us on the Road.</p>
            <p>Do you meet any then, that ſays, Tis true, your Aim is good, your Deſign pious in the Voyage you have undertaken toward Heaven and Happineſs; but are you ſure your Guide is faithful, that he will not Hand you about, or bring you into a wrong way, which will never bring you, at leaſt not ſafely, to your Journeys end? I am your Friend, (ſays he) and I ſpeak this out of Kindneſs to you, and in the Fear of the <hi>Lord,</hi> 'tis dangerous to truſt thoſe guides, that are impos'd on you by Human Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Since God himſelf has chalked you out a Way ſo Plain, that you cannot miſs it, and you have Eyes in your Head, and can ſee as well as thoſe, that call themſelves <hi>Seers in Iſrael.</hi> Have a care of ſuch a Man; Either he is out of the way himſelf, and out of a Blind Zeal endeavors to ſeduce other into the ſame Mazes and Labarynths, (for even Error it ſelf deſires Company, and loves not to be alone:) <hi>Two is better then one,</hi> is a Maxim
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51446:13"/>that all men, bad as well as good, grant and acknowledge;) or elſe he is Proud and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious, and thinks himſelf fit to Judge and Cenſure others; and would have you throw off, and diſown your ſpiritual Guides, pretending, that he himſelf has greater Sanctity and abillity for thoſe very Offices, which he would decry in others. Remember that God led his People of old by the hands of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and their ſlighting of thoſe Guides made them wander ſo long in the Wilderneſs, and ſo few of them to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the promiſed Land. And remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber alſo, that it was God, and not Man, who <hi>gave ſome Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangeliſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephiſe.</hi> 4.11.</note> 
               <hi>and ſome Paſtors and Teachers, for the prefecting of the Saints, for the work of the miniſtry</hi> for the <hi>Edifying of the Body of Chriſt;</hi> And they that ſet light by thoſe, and will have Guides of their own ſetting up, Rebel againſt God, by whom they are ſent, and can entitle themſelves to no other Leader, but to him, who is called <hi>Abaddon</hi> and <hi>Apallyon,</hi> the King of Locuſts, and the Deſtroyer of all Grace and Goodneſs. In a word, <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel</hi> may have Temples, or rather Conventicles, outwardly pargitted with the ſhew of Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and Religion, <hi>Holineſs to the Lord</hi> may
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51446:13"/>be written on the walls, but the gods within (to which Men <hi>fall down and humble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi>) are but the Calves of the People, to whoſe ſervice they conſecrate their Ear-rings and Jewels, while <hi>Jeroboam</hi> ſets up his Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and ſwallows their Eſtates. <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is a City that is at Unity within herſelf, where is that <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> in which is the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lord, which he has choſen to be an Habitation for himſelf: of which he has ſaid <hi>This ſhall be my Reſt for ever, here will I dwell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 11.21. <hi>v.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>for I have a delight therein.</hi> And that the poor may not be enveigled with the pretences of weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Hypocrites, or be moved to tranſgreſs for a peice of Bread, and (as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays in another caſe) <hi>V.</hi> 16. of that <hi>Pſalm</hi> he ſays, <hi>I will bleſs her Victuals with Encreaſe, and will ſatiſie her Poor with Bread.</hi> And that the Preiſts may not be ſtagger'd in their ſervice, nor deſert their Station in the Houſe of God, <hi>v.</hi> 17. he ſays, <hi>I will deck her Prieſts with health, and her Saints ſhall rejoyce and ſing.</hi> And that <hi>David</hi> alſo may not be diſcouraged in waiting upon his God (though perhaps an <hi>Abſalom,</hi> or <hi>Jeroboam</hi> may with glittering ſhews, and glaring falſe Pretences at once ſeduce and make the People to Sin) he ſaies, <hi>v.</hi> 18, 19. <hi>There will I make the Horn of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51446:14"/>David to flouriſh, I have ordain'd a Lanthorn for mine Anoynted; As for his Enemies, I ſhall cloath them with ſhame, but upon himſelf ſhall his Grown flouriſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, Doth any one come to you in <hi>Samuels</hi> Mantle, in the garb and poſture of a Prophet? and in that Sacred Diſguiſe falſely whiſper to you, what that Apparition ſaid truly to Saul; That God is departed from the King, and become his Enemy (for ſuch Sprights alſo there are now abroad in the World, and thoſe in black too) have a care now, and ſtand upon your Guard! Look diligently about you, are ye not got into <hi>Endor</hi> e're you are aware? Is not the Witch and the Devil at work now inſtead of <hi>Samuel,</hi> tempting you to ill Thoughts of him, whom that <hi>more ſure Word of Propheſy,</hi> the Word of God tells you, ye ſhall not dare ſo much as to think irreverently of? Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that Apparition was an Extraordinary thing, never permitted but once, a thing that frighted the Witch herſelf, and not like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be repeated again for every Fantaſtick mans-ſake, that would pretend to Inſpiration. 'Tis true indeed, there are ſuch Spirits in the World, but they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Wicked Spirits, Spirits of Rebellion and Miſcheif
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51446:14"/>and Murder, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> prophecies of, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. v. 4. <hi>Traiterous, heady, high minded, lovers of pleaſures, more than lovers of God.</hi> Such as St. <hi>Jude</hi> deſcribes, <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>who deſpiſe Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, ſpeak evil of Dignities; and theſe</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us in the foremention'd place to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> have a form of Godlineſs; they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear like <hi>Lucifer</hi> himſelf, when he is tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd into an Angel of Light, all clad with the bright and glorious Raies of pretended Sanctity, as if they were Sons of the Morning, ſome of the <hi>Corps du Guard</hi> to the great King of Heaven: But then have a Care, <hi>Mulier formoſa ſuperne Deſinit in Piſcem.</hi> Beware of the Cloven foot under the Robes of Light; for though they have the Form of Godlineſs, yet you may be ſure they deny the power of it, who endeavour to leſſen and vilify thoſe Perſons in your Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who bear the Image and Stamp of Him, from whom they derive their Authority; and while they command nothing but what is in their Commiſſion, are no leſs to be Obeyd, than he that ſent them, and ſet them over us, however are not in any caſe to be Reſiſted; for <hi>whoſoever Reſiſt, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to themſelves Damnation,</hi> Rom. 13.2. I need not tell you the ſeaſonableneſs of this
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51446:15"/>Caution, the practiſe of the men of our Age has ſaved me that labour. We too well know what they were doing, when under a Pretext of defending Religion, they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd the repealing of thoſe Laws, which are the onely Hedge and Mound for its preſervation, and under the vizor of Zeal to protect his Sacred Maieſty from Popiſh Cruelty, they went about to deſtroy him with a fanatical Rebellion. But, <hi>O my Soul, come not thou into their Secret,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 49.6.</note> 
               <hi>unto their Aſſembly mine honour, be not thou united!</hi> who ſpeak friendly to their Neighbors but ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine Miſchief in their Hearts; <hi>Deſtruction and unhappineſs are in their ways,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 28.3.</note> 
               <hi>and the way of Peace have they not known.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Therefore how great Cauſe have we to bleſs God, who has in mercy to us diſcover'd theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 6.11.</note> theſe wiles and contrivances of the Devil and his Accomplices, who in mercy, meer mercy to this Sinful and Rebellious Nation has deliver'd <hi>David his Servant from the peril of the ſword, and from the hand of Strange Children, whoſe mouth talketh of vanity and their right hand is a right hand of iniquity, who has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved him from the Blood-thirſty, and deceitful Man,</hi> from the Bloody Romaniſt, and from
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51446:15"/>the deceitful Enthuſiaſt,<note place="margin">Pſ. 5. v. 6.</note> both <hi>whom the Soul of God abhorreth.</hi> A King ſo dear to heaven, that it has ſhewn as many Miracles in his preſervation, as Hell hath produced Plots even to a Miracle for his Deſtruction. I need not tell you of the Star at his Birth, which though ſome men will not admit to be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther new or Miraculous, yet I am ſure was very ſtrange and unuſual, and was ſet there by that hand, which as it never did any thing in vain, ſo did it never beſtow ſuch Signal Remarks, but upon Extraordinary Perſons, and upon Extraordinary Occaſions. Nor need I refreſh your Memories with a rehearſal of the wonderfull Acts of Heaven in his whole Life, which though it has had its black lines of Affliction, more perhaps than any other King we read of, in the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of that Glorious Saint his Royal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Exile of Himſelf, and the whole Royal Family, in which he ſuffer'd more than I can relate, or he would have born, had he not been ſuſtain'd by the Right Hand of the Moſt High (while he was,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.26.27.</note> what St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays of himſelf, <hi>In journying often, in perils of waters, in perils of robbers, in perils by his own Countrymen, in perils by the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, in perils in the City, in perils in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51446:16"/>in perils in the Sea, in perils among falſe Brethren: In wearineſs, in painfulnes, in watchings often, in hunger and thirſt, in fasſting often, in Cold and nakedneſs; beſides thoſe things, that are without, that which came upon him daily, the Care of the Church of God:</hi> witneſs that fierce Aſſault of <hi>Militiere,</hi> which he ſo piouſly ſuſtain'd, and as generouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel'd and vanquiſh'd. Nor ſhall I inſiſt upon his ſtupendous and Miraculous Reſtauration, which we all ought gratefully to admire, though we can never reach that, which is <hi>paſt finding out.</hi> And above all, with him, the Reſtauration of our Religion, which went away and return'd with him, as if there were no God, while there was no King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and we could not ſerve and worſhip the one, as we ought to do, unleſs we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd our Homage and Allegiance to the other. And all this in meer Mercy to us; for I can ſcarce call it any to him, who ſeems to be reſtored only to new Afflictions, by the Ingratitude and repeated Rebellions and Conſpiracies of a ſtiff-necked and Hipocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Generation, who repay all thoſe Bleſſings that by him are conveyed to us, not only by reproachful and contumelious language,<note place="margin">Exod. 22.28.</note> which <hi>Moſes</hi> cals <hi>Reviling of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51446:16"/>the Gods,</hi> (which has been the frequent and too known practiſe of many in their Seditious Clubs, and Trayterous Cabals, even of thoſe perſons, who would ſeem to be Religious;) but by Atheiſtically, Sacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly and Rebelliouſly plotting and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving his Death, to whoſe Mercy and God-like Act of Oblivion, ſo many among us owe thoſe Lives, which they would yet once more Sacrifice to the God of Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, whom they have ſo long ſerved. But God, who alone gives Victory to Kings, has once more deliver'd <hi>David</hi> his <hi>Servant from the peril of the ſword,</hi> And why? <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the King putteth his Truſt in the Lord, and in the Mercy of the moſt Higheſt he ſhall not miſcarry.</hi> O Let us reioyce therefore, and triumph in the Name of the Lord our God! <hi>This is the day, which the Lord hath made, we will rejoyce and be glad in it, even in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of all thoſe, that have an evil will at Sion.</hi> And I hope I need not urge many Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to excite your Praiſe and Gratitude in this Day of our Salvation, onely let our Joy be ſuch, as becomes good Chriſtians and good Proteſtants; let us in the Words of our Orthodox and Loyal Mother the Church of England, <hi>ſhew forth our Joy,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51446:17"/>not only with our Lips, but in our Lives,</hi> that the due Sence of this great Mercy and Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance may move us all to walk more up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly, and more ſincerely before God, and make us for the future more Loyal to our King; that we may not any longer deal Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritically with the one, or Rebelliouſly with the other, but <hi>That with well doing we may put to ſilence the Ignorance of fooliſh men.</hi> That God may once more <hi>ſpeak Peace unto his People, and to his Saints, that they turn not again; that God may delight to dwell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, and glory may dwell in our Land; that</hi> we may once more <hi>go into the Houſe of God as Freinds, and worſhip God in the Beauty of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs;</hi> that there may be no more Heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burnings among us, but that we may with one Mind, and one Mouth <hi>Glorify God, even the Father</hi> of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> To whom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
